Kyle Alden

2035 Trumbull Ter NW, Washington, DC 20011 | (802) 989-5741 | kyle.alden@gmail.com

Professional Summary

I am a recognized subject matter expert in spatial data analytics, data management, and spatial visualization in the US Government. I currently serve as the Geospatial Specialist at USAID's Bureau for Resilience and Food Security where I develop analytic processes and tools to inform development programming, manage the Bureau's spatial data, and support analytic efforts to inform our flagship Feed the Future initiative. During my twelve-year tenure at the Central Intelligence Agency I provided unique insight to intelligence questions by applying geographic methods as both an analyst and a program lead and was promoted to GS-14.

Experience

JANUARY 2021 - PRESENT

United States Agency for International Development, Bureau for Resilience and Food Security | Program Officer, Geospatial Specialist

- Developed tableau-based analytic tools to support USAID's program development.
- Drove analysis to inform several country-level prioritization efforts at the Bureau
- Developed new processes to manage the bureau's core spatial data and to make it readily available throughout USAID
- Performed the role of an Agreement Officer's Representative and activity manager- driving external analytic efforts that support the Bureau.
- Calculated agrometeorological indicators--Standard Precipitation Index, Normalized
 Difference Vegetation Index, and Heat Stress Days-- in the Feed the Future program's
 twelve focus countries' zones of influence using Google Earth Engine and python scripts,

JANUARY 2019 - DECEMBER 2020

Central Intelligence Agency, Directorate of Analysis | Analytic Methodologist, Technical Lead

- Worked in consultation with analysts across several agencies to build tailored data solutions that provide automated insights into their intelligence questions
- Applied various spatial methods including spatial clustering and route modeling to intelligence problems using geospatial software and python
- Scripted new processes using python and SQL for evaluating the impact of our products
- Built and maintained Tableau dashboards allowing our team and management to keep track of key program metrics
- Briefed senior agency and IC leaders on our program and its impact

APRIL 2017 - JANUARY 2019

Central Intelligence Agency, Directorate of Analysis - Analytic Methodologist, Program Director

- Starting in 2015 I helped initiate and eventually led a program that developed a geospatial web application used throughout the intelligence community (IC).
- Defined the program's vision and priorities to ensure that it was in line with senior management's goals and provided analytic value for working level officers
- In collaboration with a developer, managed our python-based data ingest process to include gathering data from several APIs, data standardization, and loading data into our PostgreSQL and Oracle relational database systems
- Developed and documented standards for publishing GIS web services, including ensuring cartographic best practices, data standards, and maintaining data provenance
- Regularly briefed Intelligence Community seniors on program capabilities and impact
- Coordinated the work of multiple teams--including a team of front-end web developers, a team of cloud architects and developers, a team of GIS analysts, and several other analytic units--to ensure that development and analytic milestones are met
- As a Contracting Officer's Technical Representative, was responsible for a multi-million dollar contract with several geospatial web developers, GIS analysts, and a data librarian.

MARCH 2012 - APRIL 2017

Central Intelligence Agency, Directorate of Analysis - Analytic Methodologist

- Applied various GIS methods using the ArcGIS suite including suitability modeling, spatial statistics, and route modeling to intelligence problems.
- Created GIS web services--both to serve data and to serve analytic processes
- Wrote and contributed to analyses for senior US intelligence officials.
- Managed a GIS project across multiple agencies that used an automated analytic to update a map used in daily intelligence projects

SUMMER 2008, JUNE 2009 - MARCH 2012

Central Intelligence Agency, Open Source Center - Geographer

- Produced written and cartographic products using GIS data and software
- Served a customer service role providing map products and data to requestors
- Designed and taught a class on how to use geographic thinking and GIS data to better answer analytic questions

Education

ONGOING | **University of Wisconsin Madison -** MS in Cartography and GIS - GIS Development, expected graduation May 2024

FEBRUARY 2005 - JANUARY 2009 | **Middlebury College** - BA in Geography

Skills

ArcGIS Desktop, Pro, Server, and Portal, QGIS, Python, PostgreSQL, PostGIS, Adobe Illustrator, Tableau; familiarity with AWS, familiarity with R, Contract Management, Strong communication skills based on extensive professional training and in writing and briefing